STAR TREK
STRANGE
NEW
WＯRLDS
SEASON 01  #  EPISODE 10
"A Quality of Mercy"
Previously. on STAR TREK STRANGE NEW WORLDS...
PIKE: T'quiel Dawn.
UNA: You know their names.
PIKE: Muliq Al Alcazar.
MAN: Get out of here!
- Aah!
We can keep doing this. but we can also talk about it.
It's classified.
UNA: How do you know you can't make a different choice?
Yuuto Hoshide.
One that saves all of you?
PIKE: Andrea Lopez.
I accepted my fate.
It goes beyond my own life.
UNA: What if your fate...
is what you make it?
PIKE: Maybe that's the good in seeing my future.
Stay the course. Save their lives.
PIKE: Captain's Log. Stardate 1457.9.
The Enterprise is on the edge of the Neutral Zone.
A narrow band of space separating the Romulan Empire...
from the Federation.
A remnant of a treaty from 100 years ago...
when a destructive war was waged between our 2 cultures.
Enterprise and the U.S.S. Cayuga...
are here to help the outposts that guard the Neutral Zone...
with much-needed retrofitting and supplies.
[DOOR WHOOSHES OPEN]
We already had spaghetti last night.
I'm making Pasta Mama.
Just add eggs. parmesan...
lightly sauté. and it transforms from leftovers...
into something new.
- Mmm.
Little like what we're doing to these outposts.
Not as tasty. though.
Hearing rumors the Romulans are developing new weapons.
Ah. the Romulans are the boogeymen.
No one's ever seen one.
Nobody even knows what they look like...
and yet they get blamed for a lot of things around here.
Some actually their fault.
You know. I think I miss the beard.
Yeah. I...
It felt like it belonged to a different era of Captain.
Thought that's what you were going for. man out of time.
[CHUCKLES]
How have you been holding up?
Someone told me I have better places to be...
so I'm trying to be there.
Better places.
And how's that going?
You tell me.
[CHUCKLES]
Well. much as I love you being mysterious...
I've got a date on the far side of the Neutral Zone.
PIKE: Mmm.
Anyone I know?
Not that kind of date. actually.
You know. I'm making osso buco next week. if you're interested.
I mean. I'm always curious who the Chris of tomorrow is gonna be.
Beard. no beard.
Surprise me.
[CHUCKLES]
[DOOR WHOOSHES OPEN]
AL-SALAH: We are on our own out here.
How do you plan to fix our supply chain problems?
Under the proposed retrofit directive...
every outpost will be equipped...
with state-of-the-art matter synthesizers...
fueled by minerals from the asteroid itself.
They will also each receive a set...
of fully automated mining craft that can be operated remotely.
Commander?
How does this sound?
Sounds like what I've been asking for for the last 5 years.
[CHUCKLES] Well. you're welcome.
[DOOR WHOOSHES OPEN]
You know I'm working.
I just wanted to meet Captain Pike.
[CHUCKLES] Apologies.
Maat has always dreamed about joining Starfleet.
What did you say your name is?
Maat.
Maat Al-Salah.
[AL-SALAH ECHOING] He has a model of the Enterprise back home.
You're quite a hero of his.
Is it true you can tell what warp you're at...
[FADED] just by listening to the sound of the engine?
[INDISTINCT PEOPLE SHOUTING]
[ECHOING STOPS]
Apologies. I... I think I need a moment.
I'm sorry. he just gets a little excited.
It's totally fine. I'm just feeling a little under the weather.
Number One and Spock can answer any further questions you have.
[DOOR WHOOSHES OPEN]
[MUFFLED. INDISTINCT VOICES]
UNA: Captain.
[INDISTINCT PEOPLE SHOUTING]
Chris. that boy.
He's one of the names you mentioned.
Yes. I wasn't expecting that.
There's 2 cadets who don't make it. He's 1 of them.
You don't have to face this alone.
What are you going to do?
I don't know.
But I have to do something. don't I?
[DOOR WHOOSHES OPEN]
Computer.
- [COMPUTER CHIMES]
Take dictation.
Dear Maat...
I'm gratified to see your deep interest in Starfleet...
and I encourage you to pursue your dream...
but there is something you should know about...
the future?
MAN: You'll figure out how to say it.
Trust me.
Who the hell are you?
I thought that would've been obvious.
I'm you.
STAR TREK
STRANGE
NEW
WＯRLDS
SEASON 01  #  EPISODE 10
"A Quality of Mercy"
PIKE: Space.
The final frontier.
These are the voyages of the starship Enterprise.
Its 5-year mission...
to explore strange new worlds...
to seek out new life...
and new civilizations...
to boldly go...
where no one has gone before.
[ ♪ THEME MUSIC ♪ ]
Sorry.
It's just. this room brings back a lot of memories.
Is this some kind of...
Joke? No.
How am I supposed to believe...
That I'm really you?
You ever gonna let me get a word in edgewise?
I knew you were going to say that. Does that help?
I've been doing this long enough...
that I'm not just gonna take the word of somebody...
who shows up in my cabin and says he's future me.
Mmm.
Your 1ˢᵗ pony was named Sir Neighs-a-Lot.
He broke his leg in a rainstorm.
Your parents had to put him down. and you cried for a week.
Ever tell anybody that?
It's hard when your tragic backstory starts with...
A silly name.
I'm sorry.
Look...
I'm here because that letter you're about to write...
is going to wreck the future.
How. though?
Wh...
Why?
2 cadets die in that accident 7 years from now.
Maat is 1 of them.
You're trying to figure out...
how to save the cadets and yourself.
And you do.
We do.
You write to all of them. tell them not to be there that day.
But like so much of this time-bending stuff. there are. uh...
unforeseen consequences.
Well. how bad can it be...
if I figure out a way to save all the cadets and myself?
Hell. isn't you standing here evidence that I pull it off?
Yes.
And that's the problem.
Causality is complex.
The letter is just the 1ˢᵗ domino to fall...
in a chain reaction of events that leads to catastrophic results.
It alters the future...
in ways that we never intended to change.
You sound like one of those Klingon monks from Boreth.
Who do you think sent me?
They gave me something to show you.
Is that what I think it is?
A time crystal.
It will show you the effects of changing your fate.
This is serious.
This is end-of-the-world stuff.
I know that you would never...
put your own fate before the fate of the galaxy.
And that's how I convinced the Klingons...
to let me show you instead.
Instead of what?
You know the Klingons.
Nothing they wouldn't rather solve with a bat'leth.
I...
Captain?
Uh. sorry.
What was I saying?
Um. that since the age of wooden ships...
all shipmasters have had a happy privilege of...
Right.
I assume I was... I was talking about weddings?
Yeah?
Which we get to perform. as Captains...
on ships.
So...
we take you...
and you. uh...
and you...
both want to get married.
So...
- [ALARM BLARING]
COMPUTER: All decks. red alert.
Repeat. all decks. red alert.
Thank God.
SPOCK: Number One to Captain Pike.
Outpost 4 reports they are under attack...
by a space vessel. identity unknown.
Copy. Mr. Spock.
On my way.
[BOATSWAIN'S WHISTLE BLOWS]
What's the situation. Mr. Spock?
Lieutenant Uhura can brief you.
Outpost 4 reported under attack. sir.
Then message terminates.
Any word from 2 or 3?
2 has not responded to our hails...
and 3 has also gone silent.
How far out are we. Erica?
8 minutes from Outpost 4 at this velocity. sir.
Did Outpost 4 say anything else about the attacking vessel?
No identification. sir.
ORTEGAS: I'm guessing it's the same attackers. sir.
The Romulans.
Let's not make guesses just yet.
I'd like to avoid a war if I can.
Maintain course. Alert me when we're 2 minutes out.
Mr. Spock. could you join me in the Ready Room. please?
2266.
7 years into the future.
I do not understand.
Is this one of your human jokes?
I'm serious. Spock. This is...
Well. it's time crystal stuff.
Approaching this logically...
time travel seems a less likely solution...
than that you are compromised mentally.
And as your 1ˢᵗ Officer...
in these circumstances. it is my job to assume command.
I agree. if I was mentally compromised.
But I am not.
So. what's the logical solution?
Perhaps the Doctor could do a full scan.
Why don't we try a mind-meld?
That way you'll know if I'm lying or not.
My mind to your mind.
My thoughts to your thoughts.
[SCREAMING]
SPOCK: You...
carry the weight of a terrible future. Chris.
The accident in question was 6 months ago.
In this timeline...
there were no cadets at the reactor incident to save.
No one was even hurt.
I need your help. Spock.
I was sent forward to this moment in time for a reason.
We have to figure out why.
I would posit that in this present...
you were never injured in the training accident...
thus. you remained Captain of the Enterprise...
putting you in charge at a crucial moment...
in the ship's existence.
A moment where the whole future hangs in the balance.
SPOCK: All we can surmise...
is that. in the Prime future...
some other Captain of the Enterprise must have commanded it differently.
Thus. it is imperative you do not change...
what you would normally do on the ship.
I thought we were trying to avoid a terrible future.
We are trying to discover why this future is...
in the estimation of your older self. worse.
So. the only way to discover the terrible future...
is to live it.
[ENGINE WHIRRING]
ORTEGAS: Enterprise is in position and holding. sir.
Just out of weapons range.
Detecting a fair amount of debris...
but no sign of any attacking ship.
Let's triple check.
Nyota. see if there are any other Federation ships in the vicinity...
in case we need backup.
The Farragut is closest.
A couple hours away.
That's La'An's ship. sir.
Yes. I'd forgotten.
Sir. we're being hailed.
It's the outpost. Audio only.
AL-SALAH: Enterprise. can you read me?
This is Commander Hansen Al-Salah.
This is Pike. What's your status?
Outposts 2. 3. & 8 are gone.
Unknown weapon. Completely destroyed.
We had our deflector shields on maximum.
Hit by enormous power.
1ˢᵗ attack blew through our shields.
If they hit us again with our deflectors gone...
Do you read me. Enterprise?
What hit you. Commander? What vessel? Can you identify?
Negative. It all happened so fast.
And it seems to have disappeared somehow.
Switching to visual.
Enterprise. can you see?
My command post here.
We're a mile deep. on an asteroid...
[ALARM BLARING]
- almost solid iron...
and even through our deflectors. it did this.
Can you see?
- We see. Hansen.
Was your son with you?
No. thank God.
What can you tell us about the attacker?
No identity.
Only a glimpse of it.
Then it fired something at us.
High-energy plasma.
Fantastic power.
Vessel seems to have disappeared...
but it is out there somewhere.
[PANTING] Enterprise...
there's something on our sensors. moving fast.
Send us your signal.
- Switching.
Enterprise. can you see in the center of my screen?
Phasers?
- Still out of range. sir.
We're out of range. Commander. Do you have weapons?
Negative. Phasers gone.
Weapon crew are all dead.
Hail them. Warn that ship off.
I'm trying. They're not acknowledging us.
Aah!
Interesting how they became visible for just a moment.
Perhaps necessary to use weapons.
Sir. We have to find a way to engage them.
We need something to follow. Lieutenant.
We have no visuals.
Analyzing their movement patterns now.
Give me a moment.
Sir? Incoming warp signature.
We're being hailed.
- [SYSTEM CHIMING]
It's one of ours. The Farragut.
La'An's ship?
Who's hailing us?
- UHURA: Their Captain.
James Kirk.
Sam's brother?
Uh... I mean. uh...
On screen.
Enterprise. this is Captain James T. Kirk...
of the U.S.S. Farragut. offering assistance.
Christopher Pike. Good to see you. Captain.
We received Outpost 4's distress signal...
and pushed Warp 9 for as long as we safely could.
Do we know who did this?
- We have a pretty good idea.
We're trying to determine conclusively.
I may have a lead. sir.
The ship in question appears to have a kind of cloaking device.
But they still have a detectable gravitational presence.
So. can we track it. Commander...
Spock.
Theoretically. yes.
By detecting the microlensing of background stars...
we can determine an approximate location.
Impressive. Mr. Spock.
Where's the intruder now?
He has changed heading. At a very leisurely maneuver.
They may not be aware of us.
- How can that be true?
They had to decloak to fire.
Their device may work both ways.
It makes them invisible to our sensors...
but requires a massive amount of energy.
They are likely flying blind...
without enough power to run their scanners.
So. we can't see them. but they can't see us.
[BEEPING]
His heading is now 1-1-1. mark 1-4.
The exact heading a Romulan vessel would take...
toward the Neutral Zone and home.
Sir. it's the Romulans.
We have to take them out.
We can't enter the Neutral Zone. Starfleet is clear on this.
We do. that's considered an act of war.
They destroyed 3 of our outposts.
That's not an act of war?
We attack the Romulans without authorization...
the Federation will consider us expendable.
KIRK: We do have another option.
We can shadow the ship.
Follow a parallel course. to buy us some time.
Not an intercept course. sir?
- No.
The Captain is right. That would be a declaration of war.
But if Enterprise and Farragut...
match course and speed with the enemy ship. exactly...
move for move...
they might think we're just a reflection.
Echoes on their sensors.
That way we won't lose them...
while we wait to hear back from Starfleet.
Let's start shadowing them.
Uhura. send a message to Starfleet.
Ask for permission to engage the Romulans.
Captain Kirk. we'll be talking.
I look forward to it. Kirk out.
Get Sam Kirk up here. ASAP.
SAM: Am I off the record here. sir?
Jim was always at the top of his class.
He's smart and highly skilled. obviously...
but he's not above relying on charm or even luck.
Sounds like a wild card.
A whole deck of 'em.
He doesn't like to take the path everyone else does.
And he doesn't like to lose.
Should we be worried that he's going to start a war?
Look. I'm not gonna say that Jim isn't a pain in the ass.
He is. He's a huge pain in the ass.
But the truth is...
he's as fine a Captain as Starfleet has.
Okay. Good to know.
Like I said. he does like to bend the rules sometimes.
No. more like all the time.
[COMMS CHIMING]
SPOCK: Captain. can you come to the bridge?
There is something you should see.
UHURA: There's a comet ahead...
and its trail is reflecting a signal on an unused EM frequency.
It is encoded. Mr. Spock is trying to decipher.
But we think it might be from the enemy ship.
They cut off transmission. but we managed to make a copy.
I think it's the feed from their bridge. sir.
So. we're finally going to see what the Romulans look like.
Put it on screen. please. Mr. Spock.
[SOFT WARBLING]
PIKE: Captain Kirk...
welcome aboard the Enterprise.
Thanks. Captain Pike.
Sam.
Quite the ship you got here.
He's jealous.
[KIRK CHUCKLING]
Well. we're not gonna get out of this problem...
by not talking about it.
Agreed.
I'd like to hear what Mr. Spock has to say for himself.
I assure you. Lieutenant...
the similarities between Vulcans and Romulans...
came as a surprise to me.
Perhaps even more so than you.
It does seem suspicious.
Not the similarity itself...
but the fact that we should discover it right now.
What are you suggesting?
Well. it's no secret that the Vulcans and the humans...
are in alliance.
Perhaps the Romulans allowed us to see that transmission...
in hopes that it would sow discord among us.
Even if we ignore the pointy-eared elephant in the room...
we have another problem to worry about.
We're going to lose our prey.
MITCHELL: The Romulans are on a bearing...
to return to the Neutral Zone in an hour.
KIRK: I don't think we can wait.
We have to make a choice here.
SPOCK: Say we do make that choice.
Their plasma weapon can still slice through our shields.
That. in conjunction with their cloaking device...
gives them a tactical advantage.
Even against our ships working in tandem.
M'BENGA: Working in tandem for what?
To destroy them?
Say we're lucky enough to do that.
Isn't that. technically. an act of war?
ORTEGAS: I hate to say it. Doc...
but they started it.
This isn't a schoolyard.
Billions of lives are at stake here.
Which is why I want to hear everyone's opinion...
before we take any action.
I vote against war.
- ORTEGAS: So do I.
I just think that means killing Romulans.
Captain. your thoughts?
What happens when they return to Romulus...
and tell their leaders...
that the Federation won't even fight back?
I'm starting to lean toward attack.
If we allow them to destroy our outposts with no repercussions...
we run the risk of war.
Have to believe there's another way forward.
I think we should attack.
Mr. Spock?
If the Romulans are an offshoot of my Vulcan blood...
which I believe...
then attack is indeed the only option.
Vulcan. like Earth. had its aggressive colonizing period.
Savage. even by human standards.
If the Romulans retain this martial philosophy...
then weakness is something we dare not show.
Well. if Spock and I can agree...
then there's hope for all of us.
We don't all agree.
KIRK: Hold a moment. Captain Pike. that comet we're approaching...
might just be the alternative that you've been looking for.
Mr. Spock. can you put up the trajectory on screen. please?
Currently. the Romulan ship is headed for the comet's tail.
Now. I know that they're invisible...
and we can't lock on to their exact position.
But the second they go through that...
particle distortion will reveal their location.
And we'll be flanking them on either side.
KIRK: They'll be penned in. and we'll be able to get weapons locked.
Good plan. Captain.
Captain's Personal Log. Stardate 1709.2.
Per Captain Kirk's plan. we are mounting a pincer move.
Our 2 ships will slowly drift closer as the Romulans remain unaware.
When they pass through the comet's tail...
giving us their exact location...
we will be in weapons range.
Kirk. however. has agreed to my plan...
to neutralize. not destroy. the bird-of-prey...
leaving open the possibility of dialogue.
And yet I remain concerned...
this brash. young Starfleet Captain follows his own rules.
I can't help but wonder...
is Kirk the reason I was sent here?
If I wasn't here to stop him...
would we be led into a war?
Ortegas. maintain present course. but be ready.
I'll keep my foot over the gas. just in case.
SPOCK: Still tracking the gravitational presence of the Romulans.
Their trajectory remains unchanged.
Holding position.
Let us know when you see them. Enterprise.
We're passing through the tail.
Any second now.
[INDISTINCT CHATTER OVER COMMS]
Something isn't right.
The Captain is correct. We should have seen them by now.
Enterprise. I don't like this.
[BEEPING]
SPOCK: Reading gravitational signature again.
It's behind the Farragut.
Kirk. get out of there!
- Red Alert!
Red Alert. Erica. close that distance as fast as you can.
Attack pattern Tiberius 4.
Get behind them.
[ALARM BEEPING]
Fire!
[GRUNTING]
[ALARMS BLARING]
Fire phasers. Captain.
We're out of range. We're just as likely to hit you as them.
Maybe you'll draw their fire.
Mitchell. full phasers now.
Holy... We actually clipped them.
Nice shooting. Jenna.
Nyota. hail them. I want them focused on us.
Hailing. sir.
Keep firing.
MITCHELL: They're firing their plasma weapon.
Brace for impact!
[GRUNTING]
Damage to Decks 6. 7 & 9.
And weapon control is down.
That should have destroyed us. How are we still standing?
SPOCK: They were shooting at a distance.
Perhaps their plasma weapon...
is less effective when fired long range.
Status of the Farragut?
Critical. They will lose life support inside of 5 minutes.
I can get us there in 30 seconds.
Pike to Transporter. Get the pads warmed up. Chief.
We're about to test their upper limits.
[SOFT WARBLING]
Clear the pads. There's 1 more group behind us.
[SIGHS] Am I glad to see you.
Oh. um...
I didn't know you were a hugger. Lieutenant.
Oh. Commander.
Or have you forgotten?
I... Of course I haven't.
Speaking of...
when's the last time you talked to Una?
Well. I... I can't talk to her.
No one can. It...
She's not allowed contact.
Of course.
[SOFT WARBLING]
KIRK: Captain Pike.
We need to talk. Now.
You flinched.
You deliberated. and we lost.
We fired. Captain. And we were fired upon.
That's why you're still here.
From the start...
you wanted to cripple them. not take them out.
We may have different points of view...
but do not question my combat readiness. Captain.
I'm saying caution means...
you're not going to put everything you have into the punch.
And that's a good way to lose...
because your enemy will see that and act accordingly.
All this because of a second's delay?
Tell me I'm wrong. Captain...
and I will back down.
If you're saying you're more willing to take risks than I am...
I don't disagree.
And let me remind you that you're saying that on my ship...
after yours has been destroyed.
Fair.
I'm just saying. I underestimated him.
I'm not going to do it again.
[COMMS CHIMING]
SPOCK: Captains Pike and Kirk to the bridge.
There is something you'll both want to see.
[DOOR WHOOSHES OPEN]
Before they cloaked. I was able to scan the bird-of-prey.
They are trailing trilithium fragments.
Their power supply is damaged.
I do not believe they have enough to make it back to Romulus.
Do we know their position?
- SPOCK: Yes.
On a heading for the Neutral Zone.
We could overtake them.
What's the status of our weapons?
Our offensive capabilities are limited.
Phasers are down.
And torpedo launch tubes sustained damage in the attack.
But the Romulans don't know that.
They will if we pull up on their 6 and can't fire.
Lieutenant Uhura. open a channel to the Romulan ship.
Sir? They haven't responded to any of our hails before.
I know. Open a channel.
We're going to send them a message.
What are you doing?
Taking a risk.
[COMM CHANNEL CHIMES]
This is Captain Christopher Pike of the U.S.S. Enterprise.
Our 2 cultures have been at war for 100 years.
Long enough that we don't even question it.
But I believe we can make another choice.
Right now.
I'm offering you a temporary cease-fire...
so that we can talk.
For the 1ˢᵗ time in 100 years.
Okay. That was unexpected.
They want to destroy us. but they also want to get home.
Knowing what your opponent wants is key to a successful negotiation.
That's assuming they can be negotiated with.
[SYSTEM CHIMING]
Captain Pike. the Romulans are calling.
Looks like we're about to find out.
On screen. please. Nyota.
Captain Pike...
it is good to make your acquaintance.
Commander.
I know your ships attacked our outposts...
on the edge of the Neutral Zone.
But I also know...
that our 2 cultures have been at war for generations...
without ever having been face-to-face.
I don't know why your ancestors attacked Earth...
or what my ancestors did in retaliation.
I only know that we're paying a bill...
that was written long before you and I were ever born.
Perhaps it's time we reconsider the cost.
So. we can blow each other out of the sky...
using what little power we have left...
or we can try something different.
We can explain ourselves to each other.
Understand each other. Empathize.
If we don't. this war between us will simply continue. unabated.
And the cost for that is sure.
Death.
More and more death.
Our peoples are indeed different. Captain.
In our culture. your words are a show of weakness.
What chance does dialogue offer. save to delay me?
Why should I listen to you?
PIKE: Both our ships are damaged.
Your cloak is unstable...
which leaves you vulnerable to our weapons.
Maybe you have enough power to attack us.
Maybe you have enough power to get back to Romulus without repairs.
Conversely. maybe we can marshal our weapons and destroy you...
before you make it to the Neutral Zone.
Or perhaps we chase you across the border...
and destroy you and get out before anyone's the wiser.
So. what is it that you're suggesting. Captain?
A good-faith gesture.
2 hours.
Enough time to repair our ships and bury the dead.
And maybe this bit of mercy...
will lead to something further and better...
between our 2 cultures.
[SIGHS SOFTLY]
2 hours.
[EXHALES]
[SIGHS]
Captain.
They are lying.
Romulans can't be trusted.
They shot Farragut right in front of us.
Stand down. Erica.
You can't let them get away with it!
Stand down!
Yes. sir.
Sensor readings suggest...
the Romulans have stopped forward movement.
I wonder what they're doing over there.
Hopefully...
same thing we are.
SUBCOMMANDER: A cease-fire?
This is Federation weakness.
Is it not the Romulan way...
to attack when we are given advantage like this?
We are engaged in a cease-fire. SubCommander.
We have 2 hours.
Put all hands to repair our engines.
If we do not. we will not make it back to Romulus.
Sir. we should commit all hands to weapons repair.
The Federation has given us the advantage.
We can strike before this ridiculous cease-fire is completed.
This is your 4ᵗʰ mission. is it not. SubCommander?
3ʳᵈ. sir.
I served with your uncle Tarqan during the Reman campaign.
Did you know that. SubCommander?
I did.
His death was a great victory for Romulus.
Yes. he was brave.
His Commander. however. was a fool.
He forced him to fight after we'd lost weapons...
and the only logical choice was retreat.
He did not have to die.
Sir?
His death was a waste.
And it was stupid. It left us weaker.
Now. I can say that because I'm old enough...
and I don't care what people think of me.
Pride is not something we can afford.
We look at the world clearly on my ship.
We do not make choices based on ego.
Engines 1ˢᵗ.
Then weapons. That is my order.
Or are you so arrogant...
you think you know better than your Commander?
No. sir.
Good.
Because I need you.
I don't know if this peace game...
we're playing with the Federation will work.
But I have to see it through.
And if we achieve it. then good.
But if not?
Then you'll get your war.
Do you want some coffee?
I do not drink coffee. I do drink tea.
All right. Would you like some tea?
No. thank you. Captain.
[CHUCKLING]
Well. the more things change. the more they stay the same.
It's good to see you're still you. Spock.
So many things have gone wrong today.
[SIGHS]
The loss of Outpost 4. The destruction of the Farragut.
Any one of them could set us on the path to a dark future.
But I can't help feeling...
there's something worse to come.
Typically. no one can know the future in the moment.
One can only follow one's instincts...
and hope the truth will present itself.
Spock...
what happened to Una?
She was sentenced to the Federation penal colony on Salius VI...
where she has spent much of the last 7 years.
Why?
Her deception.
I am confused.
Even years ago. I thought you knew.
[DOOR CHIMES]
- Come.
SPOCK: If you'll excuse me. I wish to supervise...
the repair of the phaser array personally.
Captain.
[DOOR WHOOSHES OPENS]
I know you want me to change tack...
but pride is just not something we can afford.
You want me to tell you that I wouldn't have tried...
to blow those Romulans out of the sky?
Well. I would have.
But it wasn't my call.
Okay. We're here now.
And the truth is...
I don't know these Romulans can't be trusted.
But I also don't know if they can.
And neither do you.
Fair enough.
I'd like to explore a backup plan.
If you'll give me the resources.
I'm listening.
Look. the Romulans just bought themselves some time.
Sure. they can use that time to make repairs.
But remember. they're on the edge of the Neutral Zone.
They could also use it to call for reinforcements.
So. what if we did the same?
Just in case they decide to turn and fight after all.
Jim. we're on the far edge of Federation space.
It takes days to get a message to Starfleet.
We're weeks away from help getting to us...
even at maximum warp.
But the Romulans don't know that.
Captain Kirk...
what are you suggesting?
Captain Pike...
can I borrow a shuttle?
[SYSTEMS POWERING ON]
Try it now.
[ENGINEER IN SCOTTISH ACCENT] Aye. that's the one.
This is where the auto repair was getting hung up.
She's very fused.
I do not need to remind you that we have less than 2 hours...
to restore phaser control to working order.
ENGINEER: I'm an engineer. not a miracle worker. Mr. Spock.
2 minutes. Captain.
Status?
MITCHELL: We have engines...
but weapons systems are not back online.
Bridge to Spock. Status?
SPOCK: Working on it. Captain.
Working on it.
UHURA: 2 hours. Captain.
And... mark.
Open a channel to the Romulan ship.
Have you repaired your ship. Commander?
Have you repaired yours. Captain?
Conventional wisdom suggests...
that our next move is to resume hostilities.
To fight.
You yourself told me that in your culture...
to do anything else would be a sign of weakness.
But let me tell you a way in which humans are not weak.
Our strength comes from our willingness to see a partner...
instead of an enemy.
In our culture. that is an act...
of faith and strength...
not a failure of character.
Do Romulans have that kind of strength?
I. too. tire of endless war.
[INTERMITTENT BEEPING]
[ALARM BLARING]
Why is the fleet here? I did not call for them.
I alerted them of our situation. Commander.
The Federation showed weakness.
It is the Romulan way to strike.
You were not going to.
I took matters into my own hands.
You disobeyed a direct order.
Had you not negotiated with the Federation...
I would not have needed to.
We undertook this mission to test the strength of the Federation.
They showed us they lack it.
We should have destroyed them the moment they did.
You don't remember a time without war.
But I do.
Who wins an endless war with the Federation?
We will. Commander.
An endless war. by definition. can never be won.
Captain Pike will not trust my word now.
What does that matter?
He will be dead soon.
[SCOFFS]
Take him off the bridge.
UHURA: We're being hailed. sir.
It's the Romulan flagship.
On screen.
Human.
I am here to accept your unconditional surrender.
Nice to meet you too.
I'm Captain Pike of the Federation Starship Enterprise.
And you are?
You may address me as Praetor.
It is customary to kneel.
As I'm not a Romulan. you'll forgive me if I don't.
Now. I'm confused.
We are holding to our side of the Neutral Zone. as you are.
Yet you demand our surrender?
Captain. I have you surrounded.
Surrender or we will destroy you.
You have 1 minute to comply.
[COMM CHANNEL CLOSES]
You know. I don't like her.
Perimeter alert.
We have ships incoming. sir. Dozens.
More Romulans?
- No.
They look like ours.
I've got a secure channel from the lead ship. sir.
It's Captain Kirk.
Chris. the reinforcements you ordered?
Been 100 years since the Federation has seen the Romulans.
We didn't know what their ships looked like...
and so I figured they don't know what ours look like either.
All robotic mining craft?
Mining. hauling. Not one of them manned.
But to the Romulans...
who's to say we aren't a Federation armada?
You sneaky son of a bitch.
It's enough to bluff with. I hope.
Try not to get us in a real fight.
I'll do my best. Thanks. Captain.
It's my pleasure. Captain.
Bridge to Spock.
We really could use some phasers right about now.
How's it going down there?
- We are making progress.
The conduits are severely damaged.
PIKE: Work faster. Mr. Spock.
We're going to need weapons soon...
or we're not going to need them at all.
The Romulan Praetor is hailing us. sir.
Keep a secure channel open for Captain Kirk so he can listen in.
You ready to sell this?
Ready as I'll ever be.
By now you've probably noticed...
our armada of Starfleet Delta-class attack ships.
But we won't have to use them. will we. Praetor?
This is an act of unparalleled aggression...
on the border of our territory. Captain.
No. just a standard training maneuver...
that happened to land our fleet here the same time as yours.
You want to know what actually is an act of unparalleled aggression?
A Romulan bird-of-prey using cloaking technology...
destroying our Neutral Zone outposts.
I know nothing of what you speak.
That's okay. We'll send you a recording of it decloaking...
right before destroying Outpost 4.
[EXPLOSION ON RECORDING]
PRAETOR: I see.
[WHIRRING]
- [COMMS CHIMING]
Romulan ship is decloaking and breaking formation.
Heading our way.
Praetor. what is this?
This is a culling. Captain.
That Commander should not have allowed himself to be caught.
ORTEGAS: Sir.
It's the bird-of-prey we've been chasing.
Nyota. pause communication.
Open a channel with the Romulan Commander.
[COMMS CHIMING]
Captain.
So. we see each other once again. after all.
What are you doing?
Only what is asked of me.
I never called for that armada.
We can beam you and your crew aboard.
You don't have to do this.
It is not our way.
I regret that we meet in this way.
You and I are of a kind.
In a different reality. I could've called you friend.
What purpose will it serve to die?
We are creatures of duty. you and I.
Just 1 more duty to perform.
Do not be upset. I have accepted my fate.
Perhaps someday. my sacrifice will lead...
to an end to this conflict between us.
They're powering up weapons.
[SYSTEM CHIMING]
The Romulan Praetor is hailing us again. sir.
On screen.
Our fleet is stronger now.
And I am ready to accept your surrender.
This is really how you want to end 100 years of peace?
What do Romulans care of peace?
It means nothing to us.
And your apparent affinity for it has sealed your fate.
Thank you. Captain Pike.
If not for your weakness. we would have never known...
what easy targets your Federation would be.
Goodbye.
They're powering up weapons again.
Evasive maneuvers. Erica. Pattern Zeta-3.
Kirk. get back here. We're about to warp out.
Roger that.
Captain. warp engines aren't engaging.
Erica.
I'm sorry. sir.
MITCHELL: Sir. the drone ships are moving.
Son of a bitch.
Kirk. what are you doing?
Covering your escape. Get those engines fixed.
ORTEGAS: He's putting the drones between us and the Romulans.
[GRUNTING]
MITCHELL: Captain Kirk has beamed on board.
Engines online. Captain.
Hit it.
[ENGINES POWERING UP]
[SIGHS]
Damage report.
MITCHELL: Reports coming from all decks.
Captain.
The Romulans are broadcasting on all known subspace frequencies.
It's a declaration of war. sir.
Against the Federation.
MITCHELL: Decks 5. 11. 12 & 22 are all reporting hull breaches.
Weapons systems took a direct hit.
Spock.
Medical.
♪♪
Massive cerebral trauma.
Major blood loss.
Spinal fractures.
Radiation burns across...
40% of his body.
I'm not sure that he will recover from this.
But if he does...
he will not be the same.
FUTURE PIKE: I know what you're thinking.
I was thinking the same thing when I went through this.
That I traded my fate for Spock's?
Yes.
This isn't going to help...
but it gets worse.
This war with the Romulans.
Millions die.
So far. It's still going on.
Not only did you start something that should never have been started.
The best chance at a lasting peace...
between the Federation and the Romulans in any timeline?
Well...
turns out he's lying in a biobed.
We all want to think our future is important.
And ours. yours and mine. it is.
Just not the way you think.
Time is. uh...
It's complicated.
But the monks showed me something simple.
Every time we change the path...
he dies.
And he's got things to do.
Fate-of-the-galaxy-type things.
Paths diverge.
But I am the result of one that should never have been taken.
Thank you.
- Hey...
look at it this way.
How many people get to give their life for someone...
twice in 1 day?
See? Twice. 'cause there's 2 of us and we're both...
Yeah. I... I got it.
Got it.
[DOOR CHIMES]
[CHUCKLES SOFTLY]
Oh. yeah.
Come.
Not interrupting. am I?
No. I...
[DOOR WHOOSHES SHUT]
Not really. I'm just. uh...
talking to myself.
Fancy a drink?
Sure.
You know. uh...
I don't think I can explain it...
but I think I was supposed to meet you.
I get that feeling too.
I. uh. honestly just came by to check on you.
I'm sorry things went down the way they did.
You tried for something better.
Tried and lost.
[GLASSES CLINK]
Did it ever occur to you that sometimes...
you can't avoid a fight?
If you had just chased that Romulan ship...
from the get-go and taken it out...
maybe none of this would've happened.
You're a good Captain. Jim Kirk.
Enterprise would be lucky to have you.
You thinking of retiring?
[CHUCKLING] No.
Oh. no. No. not yet.
So...
come on over and have a seat. Captain.
Tell me about yourself.
Where are you from?
[SIGHS] I grew up in Iowa.
[FADING] My father. George. was the 1ˢᵗ Officer on the Kelvin...
before he moved to Charleston...
Computer...
- [COMPUTER CHIMES]
Delete file.
[DOOR CHIMES]
PIKE: Come.
[DOOR WHOOSHES OPEN]
SPOCK: Captain.
Am I interrupting?
- No.
I'm very glad to see you.
But you saw me only moments ago.
Right.
You left the briefing suddenly.
It was uncharacteristic.
Was it?
But now your demeanor appears changed.
Having heard the boy's name...
I cannot help but wonder if this pertains to your future.
Let's just say...
I think the universe is telling me that some fates are inescapable.
And even if I could get out of mine...
it might just fall to someone else.
Someone you know?
Yes.
Is that why you are very glad to see me?
I believe I may owe you a debt of gratitude. Captain.
Although for precisely what. I do not know.
Spock. you are...
You are very important to me.
As are you to me. Captain.
Chris.
[ ♪ MELISSA CARPER - "MAKIN' MEMORIES" ♪ ]
[DOOR WHOOSHES SHUT]
♪ I'm makin' memories ♪
[BOATSWAIN'S WHISTLE BLOWS]
♪ I'd like to remember ♪
♪ I'm meetin' new people ♪
♪ I'd like to recall ♪
♪ Some of their names ♪
♪ Like Larry and Steve ♪
♪ Yeah. I'm makin' memories ♪
♪ That I can keep ♪
♪ Tonight I'm makin' memories ♪
♪ I'd like to remember ♪
♪ I'm meetin' new people ♪
♪ I'd like to recall ♪
♪ I'm makin' memories ♪
♪ I'd like to keep ♪
♪ Yeah. I'm makin' memories ♪
♪ I'd sure like to keep ♪
Captain...
incoming message from Starfleet Command.
Captain Batel is beaming onboard.
They want you and Commander Chin-Riley...
to meet her in the Transporter Room.
Captain Batel.
I didn't think we'd be seeing each other so soon.
I know. Captain.
And for the record. I'm sorry about this.
What the hell is going on?
Under Starfleet code of conduct 587.63...
I'm arresting Commander Una Chin-Riley for violations...
of our anti-genetic modification directive.
She's an Illyrian. Chris.
I don't care what she is.
She's my...
- I don't like it either...
but I have orders.
[GUARD GRUNTS]
- Captain.
Don't.
I've known this might happen for years.
I didn't ask for this job.
I really am sorry.
So am I.
Because this isn't over.
BATEL: Energize.
[SOFT WARBLING]
%$%$
STAR TREK
STRANGE NEW WORLDS